Guide to the American Theological Library Association Records - Addendum A
Yale University Divinity School Library
American Theological Library Association Records - Addendum A
1985-2007
1991-2005
RG 163A
Yale University Divinity School Library
16
19 boxes
This record group represents the official archives of the American Theological Library Association. The archives include organizational and administrative records, board and committee records, materials from annual conferences, and ATLA publications from the period 1991 to the present. This is an addendum to the material found in Record Group 163.
American Theological Library Association
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the American Theological Library Association.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
See Record Group 163 for the earlier history of the American Theological Library Association. In 1990 ATLA was reorganized so that the Index Board and Preservation Board were placed directly under the Board of Directors. In 1991 Albert Hurd was appointed chief executive officer of ATLA. This restructuring made Executive Director responsible for all staff appointments, with the Board of Directors now construed as a policy making body that vested management of the Association in the Executive Director and his/her staff. In 1993 a three-year Association of Theological Schools Quality and Accreditation Project was launched. In 1996 Dennis Norlin was appointed Executive Director of ATLA. In 1996 ATLA acquired an underground vault at Iron Mountain/NUS in Western Pennsylvania for the long-term storage of microfilm masters. Scholarly Resources, Inc. was hired to market and distribute microfilm to libraries for scholarly use. In 1999 the final annual volume of the Index to Book Reviews in Religion (IBRR) was published in print form as the index transitioned to an online only format. In 2000 ATLA moved from Evanston, IL to new headquarters at 250 S. Wacker Drive, Chicago. In 2006 ATLA headquarters moved across the street to 300 S. Wacker Drive.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Divinity School Library was designated as the official repository for the ATLA's archives in 2000. This record group consists of a subset (1991- ) of the records that had been deposited over several years at the Presbyterian Historical Society in Philadelphia, the former repository for ATLA archives, combined with records that have since been collected by the on-site archivist at ATLA (ATLA's Archives Liaison). The basic series structure and organization of the records reflects the organization structure that has existed at ATLA since 1991, when the three boards of Index, Membership, and Preservation were merged into one Board of Directors.
The ATLA archives in this addendum are a continuation from the records contained in Record Group No. 163. The ATLA archives are complemented by two other collections at the Yale Divinity Library: the Raymond P. Morris Papers, (RG 80) and records of the ATLA Library Development Program (RG 81). Morris, Librarian of the Yale Divinity School Library from 1932-1972, was a founder of the ATLA and long-time president of the Board of Microtext. The ATLA Library Development Program provided funds to strengthen the book collections of ninety North American theological libraries between 1961 and 1966. The program was directed by Raymond Morris, and funded by the Sealantic Fund.
Series I, Board of Directors, includes Board meeting agendas and minutes, as well as materials of the Board's Executive Committee. Since the dockets for Board meetings include reports documenting ATLA activities, this series provides a concise overview of the organization's work.
Series II, Departments, includes a sub-series for each department, arranged in alphabetical order by department name: Administrative, Business Development, Electronic Products and Services, Financial Services, Index, Information Services, Member Services, and Preservation. The series also begins with a sub-series for the Executive Director, as it is the Executive Director who chairs the weekly meetings of the departmental directors, and it is to him that the departmental directors report. Records of the Executive Director include his correspondence, annual reports to the board, information about the ATLA Endowment Fund, records of his travel to maintain national and international contacts, and records of his weekly meetings with the directors.
The Administrative Department records contain general information regarding ATLA personnel matters, such as the personnel handbook, all-staff meetings, and staff get-togethers and outings (annual Holiday party, annual summer outing, staff picnics, etc.). The administrative records also contains information about facilities management, including: the move of ATLA offices from Evanston to downtown Chicago, the 15th floor build-out at 250 S. Wacker, the ICF (Interactive Conference Facility) at 250 S. Wacker, architectural plans for the 250 South Wacker build-out, and the move of ATLA offices from 250 S. Wacker to 300 S. Wacker. Records pertaining to strategic planning and association goals are also organized under the sub-series for the Administrative Department.
Business Development Department records document that department's work with vendor aggregators, and with vendors contracted to market ATLA products; product analysis reports; and efforts to better advertise ATLA products and services.
Materials documenting the creation and administration of ATLAS (Phase I and Phase II) are located under the sub-series for the EPS (Electronic Products and Services) Department. Documents related to product support for electronic products can also be found there.
Records such as annual budgets, contracts with and reports on income generated from online vendors (EBSCO, OCLC FirstSearch, SilverPlatter, Cambridge Scientific Abstracts), annual subscriptions numbers and revenue, microfilm and microfiche sales statistics, and employee orientations and benefits are all filed under the Financial Services Department sub-series, though some information about online vendors, annual subscriptions, and microfilm and microfiche sales may also be found in reports housed in the Business Development sub-series.
Within the Index Department sub-series are located records pertaining to the ATLA Religion Database (RDB), the RDB Subsets [Ten Year Subset (TEN) and Biblical Studies Subset (BIBL)], Religion Index One (RIO), and Religion Index Two (RIT). Information Services Department records document server/computer equipment general maintenance and specs, computer/server upgrades, and staff training in the use of computer programs.
Housed in the sub-series for Member Services can be found a wealth of information regarding ATLA departments, ATLA committees, ATLA interest groups, ATLA chapters, and ATLA affiliations with other organizations. The Member Services Department is responsible for member publications, which include newsletters, the ATLA website, catalogs, and membership directories. Member Services also takes photographs for ATLA whenever a photographer is needed to document ATLA conferences, meetings of the committees, staff changes, etc. In addition to the member publications, the Member Services sub-series also includes membership information for individual, student, institutional, and affiliate memberships, and records for each annual conference (conference planning materials, conference mailings, session materials, and the published Proceedings).
Preservation Department records include information relating to the On-Demand program, the monograph preservation program, and the National Endowment for the Humanities-funded microfilming grants. Also housed with the Preservation records is information regarding the Preservation Department's relationships with microfilming vendors (Preservation Resources, later called OCLC Preservation Service Centers), microfilm storage companies (Iron Mountain), and vendors marketing ATLA microform products (Scholarly Resources, Thomson-Gale). Information may also be found in the Preservation sub-series for APCAT (ATLA Preservation Program Catalog Online), though samples of APCAT as it appears on the ATLA website are filed with other ATLA website "snapshots" housed under the member publications section of the Member Services sub-series.
Series III, Committees of the Association, includes sub-series for each type of committee in ATLA: committees appointed by the Executive Director, joint committees established by the Board, advisory committees, and special committees and standing committees of the Board. Within each sub-series, the committees are arranged alphabetically by committee name. Committees appointed by the Executive Director include: Annual Conference Committee, Education Committee, Local Host Committee, Professional Development Committee, and Publications Committee. Joint committees established by the Board include: ATS/ATLA Digital Standards and Projects Committee, and the ATS/ATLA Joint Committee. Advisory committees include: Index Advisory Committee, Membership Advisory Committee, Preservation Advisory Committee, and the Technology Advisory Committee. Special committees and standing committees of the Board include: Nominating Committee and Special Committee of the Association for International Collaboration.
Series IV, Interest Groups, contains records of ATLA's Interest Groups, arranged in alphabetical order by group name, including: Collection Evaluation and Development, College and University, Judaica, Lesbian and Gay, OCLC Theological User Group, Special Collections, Technical Services, and World Christianity.
Series V, Affiliated Institutions and Organizations, includes information about each affiliated body, as well as records pertaining to their relationship with ATLA. This series also includes correspondence regarding organizations that are not affiliated with ATLA, but with whom ATLA has communicated regarding possible collaboration and affiliation.
Series VI, Regional Groups, contains records regarding the activities of ATLA regional groups, also arranged alphabetically by the group name, including: the Chicago Area Theological Library Association (CATLA), Southeastern Pennsylvania Theological Library Association (SEPTLA), and Southwest Area Theological Library Association (SWATLA).
Arrangement
I. Board of Directors, 1991-2007
II. Departments, 1985-2006
III. Committees of the Association, 1990-2005
IV. Interest Groups, 1991-2004
V. Affiliated Institutions and Organizations, 1990-2004
VI. Regional Groups, 1987-1993
Libraries -- Special collections -- Religion; Library science -- Societies, etc.; Theological libraries -- United States; American Theological Library Association
- Board of Directors, 1991-2007; Series I
  - Mid-Winter Meeting Agenda and Agenda Materials, 1991 Feb19-21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Mid-Winter Meeting, 1991 Feb19-21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Annual Conference Meetings, 1991 Jun 17-23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee, 1991 Oct 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  - Member Services Committee of the Board of Directors, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Conference Call Meeting, 1991 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1992 Jan 31-Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting of Executive Committee of the Board, 1992 Apr 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of Annual Conference Meetings; Docket, 1992 Jun 17-21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of Annual Conference Meetings; Meetings and exhibits, 1992 Jun 17-21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reincorporation in state of Illinois; Revision of by-laws, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reincorporation in state of Illinois; Revision of by-laws, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9a)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Strategic Planning Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Midwinter Meeting Docket, 1993 Feb 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes of Midwinter Meeting; Minutes and exhibits, 1993 Feb 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes of Annual Conference Meetings, 1993 Jun15-20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes of Annual Conference Meetings, 1993 Jun 15-20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board Handbook, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes of Annual Conference Meetings, 1994 Jan 28-29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Docket, 1994 Jun 14-19 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual Conference Meeting; Minutes, 1994 Jun 14-19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Presidential Correspondence; address, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Board of Directors Policy Manual, 1994-1995 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting, 1995 Jan 20-21 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Strategic Planning Meeting, 1995 Apr 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annual Conference Meeting: incl. Strategic Plan, 1995 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Presidential Correspondence - Material restricted until 2021, 1996 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Executive Director Search: Material restricted until 2021, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting, 1996 Jan 12-13 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Review of Member Services division, 1996 Jan (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Annual Conference Meetings, 1996 Jun 20-25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annual Conference Meetings Executive Session, 1996 Jun 21-25 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 1996 Jun - 1997 Apr (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 1997 May - 1998 Jul (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - ATLA Board Policy Manual, 1997 Jun (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting, 1997 Jan 17-18 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Docket, 1997 Jun 10-15 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Minutes, 1997 Jun 11-15 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Business meeting at annual conference, 19997 Jun (Box 19, Folder 1997)
  - Election Documentation, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Midwinter Meeting, 1998 Jan 16-17 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Executive session, 1998 Jan 16 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Annual Conference Meetings, 1998 Jun 16-21 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Business meeting at annual conference, 1998 Jun (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Executive Director evaluation process, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Board Handbook, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Election Documentation, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting, 1999 Jan 15-16 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Annual Conference Meetings, 1999 Jun 8-13 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mid-Winter Docket, 2000 Jan 14-15 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting Minutes, 2000 Jan 14-15 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Executive Session, 2000 Jan 15 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Dockets, 2000 Jun 20-24 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Minutes, 2000 Jun 20-25 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Executive session, 2000 Jun 25 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Annual Conference Business Meeting re. By Laws change, 2000 Jun 22 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Annual Conference Committee, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 46a)
  - President's Files; CD-Rom and Word Documents, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 46b)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Docket, 2001 Jan 18-20 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Minutes, 2001 Jan 19-20 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Executive session, 2001 Jan 20 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Election Results, 2001 Apr (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Annual Conference Meetings, 2001 Jun 20-24 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Report on History of Regional Groups, 2001 Jun (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Election Documentation, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Docket, 2002 Jan 18-19 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Mid-Winter Executive Session, 2002 Jan 19 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Docket, 2002 Jun 19-23 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Minutes, 2002 Jun 19-23 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Executive session, 2002 Jun 19 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Election Documentation, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Docket, 2003 Jan 17-18 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Executive session, 2003 Jan 18 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Annual Conference Meetings; Docket, 2003 Jun 25-29 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Presidential Correspondence; Revision of By-laws, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Board Policy Manual (3 versions), 2003-2004 (Box 14, Folder 617)
  - Interest Group Handbook; Board nomination and election handbook; schedule of responsibilities of Board officers, 2002-2004 (Box 14, Folder 618)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting; Docket, 2004 Jan 23-24 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Board Executive Session, 2004 Jan (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Board Election Ballot, 2004 Spring (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Annual conference meetings: Docket, 2004 Jun (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Mid-winter Meeting, 2005 Jan (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Mid-winter Meeting: Executive Session, 2005 Jan (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Presidential Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Annual Conference Meetings: Docket, 2005 Jun (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Mid-winter Meeting: Board Docket, 2006 Jan (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Mid-winter Meeting: Executive Session, 2006 Jan (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Report prepared for ATLA Direct Inspection Team for Products, 2006 Jan (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Annual Conference meetings, 2006 Jun (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Annual Conference meetings: Executive Session, 2006 Jun (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Mid-winter Meeting: Docket, 2007 Jan (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Additional Documents, 2007 Jan (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Mid-Winter Meeting: Executive Session, 2007 Jan (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Report of ATLA Direct Inspection Team Triennial Review of Personnel, 2007 Jan (Box 19, Folder 11)
- Departments, 1985-2006; Series II
  - Executive Director Records
    - Reports
      - Annual Report, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Annual Report to the Board; Log of Program Committee meeting; correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Annual Report to the Board (Incomplete), 1993 Jun - 1994 Jan (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Annual Report to the Board (Incomplete), 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Report on Ethics Index Product, ca. 1996 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - Historical Overview of ATLA Board Monitoring Process, Strategic Plan 1998-2000, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Second Quarter Report FY 1997, 1996 Dec - 1997 Feb (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Fourth Quarter Report FY 1997, 1997 Jun - Aug (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - First Quarter Report FY 1998, 1997 Sep - Nov (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Second Quarter Report FY 1998, 1997 Dec-1998 Feb (Box 3, Folder 92)
      - Fourth Quarter Report FY 1998, 1998 Oct 21 (Box 3, Folder 93)
      - Third Quarter Report FY 1999, 1999 Mar-May (Box 3, Folder 94)
      - Fourth Quarter Report FY 1999 (incomplete copy), 1999 Jun-Aug (Box 3, Folder 95)
      - Draft Introduction and Outline for 1998 Annual Report (Box 3, Folder 86)
      - Statements on ATLA Policy Governance, Carver Policy Governance Model, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Annual Report, 2000 Sep 1- 2001 Aug. 31 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Annual Report, 2001 Sep1-2002 Aug 31 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Annual Report, 2002 Sep 1-2003 Aug 31 (Box 3, Folder 89)
      - Annual Report, 2003 Sep 1-2004 Aug 31 (Box 3, Folder 90)
      - Annual Report, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 91)
      - Quarterly reports, 2005-2006 (Box 14, Folder 620)
    - Communications
      - "A Leader in the Information Age" Brochure for Annual Giving Fund and Endowment Fund, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 97)
      - Correspondence, including regarding endowment fund and retired ATLA members, 1993-1994 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Endowment Fund, general informational brochures (Box 3, Folder 98)
      - Endowment Fund, brochure for North Suburban Library Foundation (Box 3, Folder 99)
      - Correspondence, memos, 1993-1996 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence and other information regarding reorganization of ATLA business operations, 1995 Nov (Box 3, Folder 96)
      - Executive Director Calendar and List of President Responsibilities, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 100)
      - Draft of ATLA Crisis Communication Plan, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 101)
      - Memo to staff regarding implementation of quarterly performance evaluations, 1998 Feb 24 (Box 3, Folder 102)
      - Correspondence regarding collaboration with OCLC, 1998 Mar (Box 3, Folder 103)
      - News releases segarding staff appointments and ATLA general facts, 1998 Sep (Box 3, Folder 104)
      - Wabash Center Consultation on Teaching and Learning for Theological Libraries, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - Correspondence with Lilly Endowment, 2001 Apr- 2002 Feb (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - Presentation at 2003 NFAIS Conference, 2003 Feb (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Administrative Department
    - Personnel
      - Policies Handbook, circa 1994 (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Personnel Handbook, 1998 Mar (Box 3, Folder 109)
      - Personnel Handbook, 2000 Dec (Box 3, Folder 110)
      - Personnel Handbook, 2003 Sep (Box 3, Folder 111)
      - ATLA Internal Web-Site: Main Page and Administration Department Page on Internal Web-Site (Printed from ATLA Internal Web-Site on 12/2/05), 2005 Dec 2 (Box 3, Folder 112)
      - ATLA Life Safety Procedures, Circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 113)
      - Emergency Response Team Pages From ATLA Internal Web-Site (Printed from ATLA Internal Web-Site on 12/2/05), 2005 Dec 2 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Facilities Management
      - Lease of Office Space in Evanston, IL, 1997 Jun (Box 3, Folder 115)
      - Facility Analysis, 1998 May (Box 3, Folder 116)
      - Relocation to 250 S. Wacker, Chicago, 1999 Dec (Box 3, Folder 117)
      - Lilly Grant for Interactive Conference Facility (ICF), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 118)
      - Interactive Conference Facility advertising brochure, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 119)
      - Relocation to 300 S. Wacker, Chicago, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 611)
    - Strategic Planning/ Association Goals
      - Strategic Plan: 1998-2000, 1999 Sep 10 (Box 3, Folder 120)
      - Strategic Planning Meeting, 1991 Aug 8, 9 (Box 3, Folder 121)
      - Strategic Plan for 1991-1994 (Draft), 1992 Jan (Box 3, Folder 122)
      - Strategic Planning Meeting, 1995 Apr 3-4 (Box 3, Folder 123)
      - Grant Proposals submitted to the Henry Luce Foundation, Inc., 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 124)
      - Lilly Grant for Association software to allow full internet capability and indexing, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 125)
      - ATLA Religion Database trademark, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 126)
      - Correspondence regarding possible RIO trademark infringement, 1997 Apr-May (Box 3, Folder 127)
      - Correspondence regarding efforts to establish international relationships, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 128)
      - Trip by John Bollier, Director of Development, to Europe to explore production issues and potential new partnerships, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 129)
      - Efforts to obtain legal permissions to reproduce scholarly materials in religion, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Business Development
    - Vendor relations
      - Agreements With DIALOG, 1984-1994 (Box 3, Folder 131)
      - Publishing agreements and advertising with Scarecrow Press for ATLA Bibliography Series and ATLA Monograph Series, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 132)
      - Agreement with Asbury Theological Seminary to develop web-based version of ATLA Religion Database, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 133)
      - Database Supplier Agreement with OCLC for ATLA Religion Database, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 134)
      - Electronic Publishing Agreement with OVID for distribution of ATLA Religion Database, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 135)
      - ATLA Religion Database added to SilverPlatter – Press Release, 1998 Mar (Box 3, Folder 136)
      - Correspondence regarding Mounting of ATLA Religion Database on Cambridge Scientific Abstracts IDS (Internet Database Service), 1999 (Box 3, Folder 137)
      - Catholic Periodical and Literature Index (CPLI) Partnership Project, 1994-1999 (Box 3, Folder 138)